<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The declaration of Captain Hotham sent to the Parliament, wherein hee sheweth the reasons of his marching into the county of York, with some troops of horse and foot, as also why he consented not to the treaty of peace agreed upon by some of the gentlemen of that county. Imprimatur, H. Elsyng. Cler. Parl. Dom. Com.</title>
            <author>Hotham, John, Sir, d. 1645 Jan. 2.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86591</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2902B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E121_32</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22715</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871821</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871821</idno>
            <idno type="VID">124238</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86591)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 124238)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 21:E121[32])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The declaration of Captain Hotham sent to the Parliament, wherein hee sheweth the reasons of his marching into the county of York, with some troops of horse and foot, as also why he consented not to the treaty of peace agreed upon by some of the gentlemen of that county. Imprimatur, H. Elsyng. Cler. Parl. Dom. Com.</title>
                  <author>Hotham, John, Sir, d. 1645 Jan. 2.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Best,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>October 11. 1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Yorkshire (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:124238:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:124238:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->
            <p>THE DECLARATION Of Captain HOTHAM Sent to the Parliament, wherein hee ſheweth the Reaſons of his march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the County of <hi>York,</hi> with ſome troops of Horſe and Foot, as alſo why he conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not to the treaty of Peace agreed upon by ſome of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of that County.</p>
            <p>Imprimatur, <hi>H. Elſyng. Cler. Parl. Dom. Com.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Richard Beſt,</hi> October 11. 1642.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:124238:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:124238:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
            <head>The Declaration of Captaine <hi>Hotham,</hi> ſent to the Parliament, wherein he ſheweth the Reaſons of his marching into the County of <hi>York,</hi> with ſome Troops of Horſe, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas divers ill-affected Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſeeking the ruine of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and the publique libertie have procured illegall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions to be iſſued out unto them thereby to get a colour to deceive thoſe that naturally ſift not into the bottome of their pretences and to perfect their De. deſignes, have by feare and terrour cauſed divers perſons to ſend in their arms and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for them to make uſe of. And whoſoever
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:124238:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 7 -->refuſed to ſecond them in their violent cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, they have of ſome ſeized their perſons, and of others plundred their houſes, as of Maſter <hi>Carter</hi> the Miniſter, <hi>Thomas Lake</hi> of (<hi>Caſtleford,</hi> and divers others during the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and M. <hi>Nevill</hi> hath made Proclamation in <hi>Wakefield,</hi> that whomſoever ſhall not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt them, themſelves, wives and children ſhall be ſeized on, and their houſes razed to the ground To prevent theſe mighty vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies, and to give a ſtop to theſe miſeries, that the Subjects every where groaned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I was forced to make uſe of that power and authority the Parliament the great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector of the Oppreſſed) had put into my hands, to march into this County with ſome troops of Horſe and Foot, and to give a breathing to theſe Oppreſsions. In purſuance of which, contrary to my Order, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Command, the unruly ſouldiers have committed ſome miſdemeanours, for which there have bin divers puniſht, and all care ſhal hereafter be taken to keep them in order and obedience. And my not obſerving the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:124238:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 7 -->laſt pacification, I expreſly declared, that I could never give my conſent to anything, wherein the Parliament adviſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent was not firſt asked, neither doe I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it to be by any generall conſent ſeeing there was ſix for the Weſt-riding, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for the North and Eaſt. And that all liberty is given to tranſport the Ordnance now in this County to the King, to the great diſ-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Parliament, and an aſſociation to 07 obey neither as if the County were indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant to the King, Parliament, or the reſt of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>And I doe here profeſſe, I have no other end in this buſineſſe, but to give aſsiſtance to thoſe that are by violence oppreſſed, for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their duties in performing the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the Parliament, and bringing to puniſhment thoſe that have been the cauſers of all theſe unhappy breaches betwixt the King and his people, and have beene ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by Parliament. For the effecting of which I doubt not of the aſsiſtance of all thoſe that are ſenſible what it is to have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:124238:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->Religion or Liberty, but at other mens pleaſures. This I thought fit to teſtifie to the World, that men may be no more deluded with ſpecious pretences. And this is all that I aime at, and therefore have ſent abroad this Declaration, atteſted under my hand.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iohn Hotham.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Cawood</hi> 
                  <date>6. <hi>Octob.</hi> 1642.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:124238:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
